Okay, moving on to dementia and degenerative disorders.
The key focus here is going to be on the word degenerative,
and what you need to understand is that in these particular disorders,
what's going to happen is you're going to lose or degenerate neurons.
Now, let's go back to just a little bit of basics.
So imagine for a moment that this is a coronal section through the brain.
Of course, you have gray matter, and then underneath that gray matter, there's white matter,
and then, of course, for example, here are ventricles, so there are two ventricles here,
so these would be the lateral ventricles, and then adjacent to the ventricles,
you often have additional gray matter.
Now, this additional gray matter represents the deeper neurons present within the brain,
and what you need to know about the degenerative disorders is that you're going to obviously degenerate neurons,
and so the degeneration can occur up here in the cortex,
and when you degenerate the neurons of the cortex, that's going to result in dementia.
In addition, you can degenerate the neurons in the deeper structures of the brain,
and in particular, the key structure that we're going to focus on is something called the basal ganglia.
The basal ganglia are neurons present within the deeper brain that are important for movement,
and therefore, if you degenerate the neurons of the basal ganglia, that's going to result in movement problems.
And so this is the paradigm that you need to have in your mind concerning the degenerative disorders.
Now, of course, I'm going to give you much more detail as we move forward,
but this is just to lay down a basic principle in your mind.
Now, with that, let's begin to text.
So I say that degenerative disorders are characterized by the loss of neurons,
and, of course, that's going to be within the gray matter,
and you can lose neurons within the cortex,
and when you lose neurons within the gray matter of the cortex,
that's going to result in dementia,
or you can lose neurons within the brainstem and the basal ganglia,
but really the key idea here is the basal ganglia,
and when you lose these neurons, that's going to result in movement disorders.
The first of these disorders is Alzheimer's disease.
This is a degenerative disease which involves the cortex,
in particular the neurons present in the gray matter of the cortex,
and, of course, when you involve the cortex, you're going to create dementia, as I've just explained.
And it so happens that Alzheimer's disease is the most common cause of dementia.
Now, to understand Alzheimer's disease, you do need a little bit of a background,
so let's take a step back.
This is a neuron, and I'm drawing for you the cell membrane of the neuron,
and present on this cell membrane of the neuron is a receptor,
which is derived from a protein called amyloid precursor protein.
Now, we don't know what this receptor does,
but what we do know is that when this receptor is being broken down,
remember that it's a protein that's going to be used,
and over time it's going to be broken down and then recycled.
So when this protein is broken down, it normally is broken down by an alpha secretase enzyme,
which results in an alpha byproduct, which can then be turned over without any problem.
However, sometimes it can be broken down by a beta secretase,
which results in a beta product,
and the problem with that beta product is that it cannot be turned over,
and instead it deposits as an amyloid,
and this is called A-beta amyloid.
So A-beta amyloid, when it's produced, cannot be broken down,
and then it begins to deposit within the brain,
and it's the deposition of A-beta amyloid that then results in Alzheimer's disease.
Again, very simplistically, amyloid precursor protein gets cleaved.
That results in A-beta amyloid.
A-beta amyloid deposits within the brain, resulting in Alzheimer's disease.
The clinical features of Alzheimer's disease are all based on dementia.
Now remember, dementia is memory loss plus cognitive dysfunction without any loss of consciousness.
So this is sort of the definition of dementia.
And so these patients get a slow-onset memory loss.
It's important to note that it's slow-onset.
It takes years to develop.
And it begins with recent memory, and then it progresses to distant memory.
Over time, they get progressive disorientation.
They begin to develop cognitive dysfunction and begin to lose motor skills and language skills.
In addition, they can develop behavior or personality changes.
Eventually, the patients become mute and bedridden.
And what's very important to note about Alzheimer's disease, especially early in the disease,
is you do not get focal neurologic deficits.
So for example, you wouldn't see features of Parkinson's disease, such as a pill-rolling tremor, or akinesia, or an expressionless face.
In addition, you wouldn't see features of Huntington's disease, like chorea, which are these random purposeless movements of proximal muscle.
So focal neurologic deficits will not be seen early in this disease.
When you consider the epidemiology of Alzheimer's disease, most cases are sporadic.
I'd like to go take a step back and just remind you that if this is Alzheimer's disease, you have the sporadic form,
and then you also have something called the early form.
Now, the key feature in the sporadic form is that the major risk factor is age.
So with time, there's an increased risk of developing the sporadic form.
And, of course, this sporadic form is predominantly a disease of the elderly.
Another important association here is that the risk is increased with the epsilon-4 allele of apolipoprotein E.
And that's particularly high yield.
Board examiners really like to go after that.
This epsilon-4 allele increases the conversion of amyloid precursor protein to the beta form.
And that then, of course, results in extra deposition of that beta form, resulting in A-beta amyloid, which then, of course, results in Alzheimer's disease.
And another thing that examiners like you to know is that there is a decreased risk with the epsilon-2 allele of apolipoprotein E.
And so that's a particularly high yield association.
Now, if you're having trouble remembering that, it's kind of easy because 4 is higher than 2.
And so 4 has the increased risk, and the epsilon-2 has a decreased risk, if that helps you.
The second important form is the early onset form.
And in the early onset form, you don't necessarily see this in the elderly, but you see it in patients who are younger.
And that's what we mean by early onset.
Now, the key important associations here are, number one, there is a familial form in which patients have a genetic mutation that's transferred through the family.
And the key genetic mutation that results in early onset Alzheimer's disease is called presenilin.
Now, there are two genes that can be involved, presenilin-1 and presenilin-2.
And the key mutation is actually present within presenilin-1.
So mutations in presenilin-1 can result in familial cases of Alzheimer's disease, which would give you early onset of disease.
The second association here is that there's an increased risk of the early form in patients with Down syndrome.
In fact, by the age of 40, a large number of patients with Down syndrome will have developed Alzheimer's disease.
Now, this is particularly high yield, and examiners love to go after it.
One of the essential principles here is that, of course, in Down syndrome, you have three copies of chromosome 21.
And remember, and very high yield, that the amyloid precursor protein that eventually results in the formation of the A-beta amyloid is actually present on chromosome 21.
And so, because the patients with Down syndrome have three copies of chromosome 21, they have an extra copy of the amyloid precursor protein,
and hence there is an increased production of the A-beta amyloid.
And so that, again, is a particularly high yield board association.
Now, with that in mind, let's go back and read the text.
So we say that most cases are sporadic.
The sporadic form is seen in the elderly.
The key risk is age.
There's also an association with the epsilon-4 allele of apolipoprotein E.
Of course, the epsilon-4 is associated with an increased risk, and the epsilon-2 allele is associated with a decreased risk.
Early onset Alzheimer's disease would be seen in younger patients.
One key association is that there is a set of familial cases, the major mutation here being in a gene called presenilin-1.
The second association here is Down syndrome, and the major issue here is that the amyloid precursor protein is present, of course, on chromosome 21,
and so that's particularly high yield to be aware of.
When a patient develops Alzheimer's disease, there are a few classic pathologic features that will arise within the brain.
Now, it doesn't matter whether you're talking about the sporadic form or the early form.
The pathologic features are similar.
However, we do need to be aware of them, and so this first image highlights one important pathologic feature,
and that is that you get diffuse cerebral atrophy of the brain.
Now, very important to note that this cerebral atrophy will be diffuse.
When you get this atrophy, a few important changes occur.
First of all, can you see these folds running across the brain here?
These are called the gyri, and one of the key findings is that you're going to get narrowing of these gyri,
and so that's one of the hallmarks of atrophy.
In addition, notice that you've got these spaces here between the gyri, here and here, for example, and here.
These are called the salsi, and so the second finding will be that you'll get widening of the salsi.
So, again, diffuse atrophy with narrowing of the gyri and widening of the salsi.
Now, a consequence of this atrophy, which is not shown on this slide but is important to know,
is that because you're losing brain mass, the ventricles are actually going to dilate and take up some of that space.
And so when you get dilatation of the ventricles due to loss of brain mass, we call that hydrocephalus ex-vacuole.
And that's an important point to be aware of, so that in this particular case,
were we to cut through this brain and look at the ventricles,
we would notice that there is dilation of the ventricles, and so, again, hydrocephalus ex-vacuole.
Now, that's not due to any increase in CSF.
Instead, it's actually due to atrophy of the brain with loss of parenchyma.
The next important pathologic finding is that there will be development of something called a neuritic plaque.
Now, here, I'm highlighting for you a neuritic plaque, and a neuritic plaque has two major components.
The first is that it has A-beta amyloid, and so you can see that there is this pink material, which represents amyloid.
Of course, this material is extracellular, because amyloid is always extracellular.
And this pink material, as it deposits, it begins to entrap neuritic processes,
so that within here, you're also going to have neuritic processes.
And so we call this whole thing a neuritic plaque, and it's a combination of A-beta amyloid with entrapped neuritic processes.
Now, important to note that this A-beta amyloid is actually derived from amyloid precursor protein.
A second important point to note, which is not highlighted on this image,
is that this A-beta amyloid can also deposit around blood vessels within the brain.
And when it deposits around blood vessels within the brain, we call that cerebral amyloid angiopathy.
Now, the problem with this deposition is that it then weakens the wall of the blood vessel,
which increases the risk for hemorrhage into the brain.
And so that's a particularly high-yield association as well, i.e. cerebral amyloid angiopathy.
The third pathologic hallmark of Alzheimer's disease is the formation of something called neurofibrillary tangles.
Now, notice that I've highlighted for you here a neuron.
Now, this is the nucleus of the neuron.
And within this neuron, you can see all these delicate fibers running through the cytoplasm,
which is sort of creating this flame-shaped edge to the cell.
And so what's happening here is that you've got deposition of something called a neurofibrillary tangle within the cytoplasm of the cell.
Now, board examiners like you to know that present within this neurofibrillary tangle is a protein called tau.
Tau is a microtubule-associated protein.
It helps to organize the microtubules, which are part of the cytoskeleton, within the cytoplasm.
In this particular case, what happens is this tau becomes hyperphosphorylated.
And when it becomes hyperphosphorylated, it can no longer assist in the organization of those microtubules.
And so you get these funny neurofibrillary tangles within the cytoplasm of the cell.
Now, board examiners like you to know that within the neurofibrillary tangle, it's going to be hyperphosphorylated tau.
And that's particularly high yield.
The diagnosis of Alzheimer's disease is a presumptive diagnosis.
It's made clinically, but only after excluding all other causes of dementia.
Now, the final confirmation, however, requires pathology.
So it would be done at autopsy.
However, of course, autopsy is often not available.
But the true final diagnosis of Alzheimer's disease is actually both clinical and pathologic.
And you put all of that data together to give a final true diagnosis of Alzheimer's disease.
An additional type of dementia is called vascular dementia.
The idea here is that you've got a problem with the blood vessels.
For example, hypertension, atherosclerosis, vasculitis, which decreases blood flow to the brain.
That decreased blood flow to the brain will result in multifocal infarction and injury.
And that will eventually result in dementia.
Now, the way I think about this is to simply go back and remind myself that when you have global cerebral ischemia,
which, again, was one of the cerebrovascular disorders that we covered,
I told you at that point that you can get mild, moderate, or severe global cerebral ischemia.
And in the case of moderate, I told you that you would get damage to areas of selective vulnerability.
For example, one of the areas that was going to get damaged was layers 3, 5, and 6 of the cortex,
which represents the pyramidal neurons.
Now, imagine if you're knocking out pyramidal neurons from the cortex,
what you're really doing is knocking out the gray matter of the cortex.
And, of course, that could eventually result in a dementia.
In addition, recall that I told you that another select region of damage would be the hippocampus of the temporal lobe.
Now, when you damage the hippocampus of the temporal lobe, you're going to create problems with memory.
And, of course, memory is also an essential component of dementia.
And so vascular dementia, one way to think about it, is that it is a consequence of moderate global cerebral ischemia.
And, of course, this is important because if it's a vascular dementia,
you might be able to alleviate the vascular problem and, therefore, improve the patient's symptoms and prognosis.
So this is important to know that it is a relatively common cause of dementia in the elderly.
Picks' disease is another degenerative disease of the cortex.
However, what's important to note is that this predominantly involves the frontal and temporal cortex
and spares the parietal and occipital lobes.
The way I think about this is that in Picks' disease, it picks the frontal and temporal cortex.
Now, this is important because, remember, in Alzheimer's, we had diffuse atrophy of the cortex.
And here, it's going to be the frontal and temporal cortex.
Now, the consequence of this is that when you knock out the frontal cortex,
you're going to develop problems with behavior.
And when you knock out the temporal cortex, you're going to get problems with language.
And so along with dementia, you get early behavioral and language symptoms.
Now, were you to examine the brain microscopically,
you would see round aggregates of tau protein within the neurons of the cortex.
Now, recall that tau protein is a microtubule-associated protein.
It helps the microtubules of the cytoskeleton arrange themselves properly.
And in this particular case, you're going to get these round aggregates of tau protein.
Now, recall in Alzheimer's disease, we also had tau protein, which was forming neurofibrillary tangles.
But we didn't get round aggregates.
We got the neurofibrillary tangles.
In this particular disorder, we have tau protein.
Instead, it's going to produce these round aggregates.
And that's particularly high yield as well.
So, switching gears a little bit, Parkinson's disease is a degenerative disorder in which you lose neurons.
However, instead of losing neurons predominantly in the cortex,
you actually lose neurons in the deeper gray matter structures of the brain.
Now, one of the most important gray matter structures in the deep brain is the basal ganglia.
The basal ganglia helps to regulate movement.
We'll talk about that in a minute.
And in this particular case, i.e. Parkinson's disease, you are going to lose the dopaminergic neurons
in the substantia niagara pars compacta, which is part of the basal ganglia.
Now, in order to really understand this, we have to go to the whiteboard.
Let's remind ourselves that the cortex communicates with the basal ganglia.
And the basal ganglia then sends its input back into the cortex.
And the purpose of this loop is to help to regulate movement.
Now, the key processing center of the basal ganglia is called the striatum.
And what you need to know about the striatum is that the striatum has the ability to send
stimulatory signal to the cortex or inhibitory signal to the cortex.
Now, in addition to receiving input from the cortex, the striatum also receives input
from the substantia niagara pars compacta.
And the dopaminergic neurons in particular of the substantia niagara pars compacta
will release dopamine.
Now, when they release dopamine, binding of D1 receptors on the striatum
will result in extra stimulation to the cortex.
And binding of D2 receptors will result in decreased inhibition of the cortex.
And so the overall effect of dopamine is to increase stimulation to the cortex
and decrease inhibition to the cortex.
And both of those are going to work to increase cortical function
so that you can increase movement.
And so the substantia niagara pars compacta has an effect on the striatum.
This whole thing, by the way, is called the niagara striatal pathway.
And this pathway helps to initiate movement by increasing the overall signal to the cortex.
Now, imagine if you knock out the dopaminergic neurons of the substantia niagara pars compacta,
which is what happens in Parkinson's disease,
you're not going to get this increased stimulation to the cortex.
And that's going to result in the movement disorders that are seen in Parkinson's disease.
Now, with that background, we can go back and read the text.
And so, again, I tell you that Parkinson's disease is a degenerative loss of the dopaminergic neurons
in the substantia niagara pars compacta, which is part of the basal ganglia.
This is a relatively common disorder.
The key risk factor is aging.
We don't know the etiology.
Historically, however, there were rare cases related to exposure to this molecule called MPTP,
which was a contaminant in illicit drugs.
And board examiners like you to know that MPTP can result in Parkinson's disease.
The clinical features of Parkinson's disease are all based on the fact that you've knocked out
the dopaminergic input to the striatum, in particular, the dopaminergic neurons of the substantia niagara.
And, of course, with that decreased input to the striatum,
you're going to have decreased input to the cortex,
and so you're not going to be able to generate movement as well.
In particular, these patients get tremor.
It's a pill-rolling tremor at rest that disappears with movement.
They get rigidity.
This is this cogwheel rigidity of their extremities.
They get akinesia, bradykinesia, which is slowing of all voluntary movements.
One example of this would be that they get an expressionless face,
as if they can't move even the muscles of the face to smile, for example.
And then they can get a shuffling gait, again, because they're not able to establish their movement,
and they get postural instability.
All of this can be remembered by the mnemonic TRAP, T-R-A-P.
Here's a picture of the pigmented neurons of the substantia niagara,
and you can see that here you've got the normal pigmented neurons present within the substantia niagara.
Here's a specimen from a patient with Parkinson's disease.
Notice that you've lost the pigmented neurons in the substantia niagara,
in particular, the dopaminergic neurons in the substantia niagara pars compacta.
The key finding is that within the neurons of the substantia niagara,
you're going to see these round eosinophilic inclusions, which are called Lewy bodies.
Now here, I've highlighted for you a neuron,
and notice that within this neuron, you've got this round structure,
which is called a Lewy body.
And board examiners like you to know that this Lewy body is composed of alpha-synuclein,
very high yield.
This round Lewy body is composed of alpha-synuclein,
and again, that's the hallmark of Parkinson's disease.
One last high yield point is that over time,
patients with Parkinson's can develop dementia.
It's relatively common.
However, it is seen late in the disease.
For example, years into the disease.
If a patient has early onset dementia,
for example, within the first year of diagnosis,
that suggests a different disorder, which is called Lewy body dementia.
And what's important about Lewy body dementia is that,
of course, you get dementia with Parkinson's-like features.
They can also have hallucinations.
However, they get cortical Lewy bodies,
which means that they have a lot of Lewy bodies within the gray matter of the cortex.
And, of course, when you knock out the cortex,
that's what's going to give you the dementia.
So, late dementia is part of Parkinson's disease.
Early dementia, for example,
within one year of the development of Parkinsonian features,
would not be called Parkinson's disease.
Instead, it would be called Lewy body dementia,
and that's because you've got Lewy bodies in the cortex of the brain.
Huntington's disease is another degenerative disorder of the basal ganglia.
However, in this particular case,
you knock out the GABAergic neurons in the caudate nucleus of the basal ganglia.
Now, this requires a little bit of review,
so let's remind ourselves that the cortex
is going to provide signal to the basal ganglia.
And, in particular, remember we said that it was the striatum of the basal ganglia.
And the basal ganglia, i.e. the striatum of the basal ganglia,
is then going to send message back to the cortex,
which is going to help to regulate movement.
Now, what's important to note is the striatum
is actually composed of two major gray matter structures.
The first is the caudate, and the second is the putamen.
So, it's the caudate plus the putamen that forms the striatum.
Now, imagine if you knock out the GABAergic neurons of the caudate,
you're going to lose an important component of the striatum,
and this is then going to result in a movement disorder
because you've damaged the basal ganglia.
Now, one additional high-yield point to know,
and board examiners like to go after it,
is that GABA is an inhibitory neurotransmitter.
So, that the GABAergic neurons of the caudate nucleus
actually provide an inhibitory signal to the cortex.
Now, the idea here is that your cortex is designed to move
and fire muscle very quickly.
Basically, imagine if you're playing baseball
and you need to quickly move to be able to catch the ball.
You don't want to have to think about it.
You want to be able to have the circuit fire
and the muscles move very quickly.
However, you also don't want random firing of the circuit
so that muscle begins to fly in different directions.
And so, you've got this inhibitory hold that's necessary
which occurs via the GABAergic neurons.
Now, imagine if you lose the GABAergic neurons,
you lose the inhibitory hold,
and when you lose the inhibitory hold,
what's going to happen is you're going to get
this random firing of the system
which is going to lead to random movements of muscle,
which is called chorea.
And so, the key problem in Huntington's disease
is you lose the GABAergic neurons of the caudate nucleus.
When you lose the GABAergic neurons,
you lose the inhibitory hold on the cortex.
When you lose the inhibitory hold on the cortex,
you're going to get random firing of the system
which is going to result in random purposeless movements
of the muscles, which is then called chorea.
Now, let's go back and review the text.
And so, I say that in Huntington's disease,
you get loss of the GABAergic neurons
in the caudate nucleus,
and of course, that's a key component of the basal ganglia.
This is a normal coronal section of brain,
and from this, I'd like to highlight
a few important principles of neural anatomy.
Now, of course, this is the gray matter of the cortex.
This is the white matter of the cortex.
These are the deeper gray matter structures of the brain.
Notice that you've got two ventricular spaces here and here.
So, therefore, this must be the lateral ventricle,
and this must also be the lateral ventricle.
And one thing that I'd like to highlight here
is notice that you've got this gray matter structure here,
which is pushing in and indenting the surface of the lateral ventricle.
Now, when you've got a big gray matter structure
that pushes in and indents the surface of the lateral ventricle,
that tells you that that's the caudate nucleus.
Now, underneath the caudate,
what you're seeing here is the putamen,
and you've got this stripe of internal capsule
going between the caudate and the putamen,
and this entire region here is called the striatum.
Basically, the caudate plus the putamen equals the striatum.
It's called the striatum because you've got this stripe
running through the center of it.
Now, of course, the striatum is the major processing center
of the basal ganga, which receives input from the cortex
and then sends input back to the cortex,
and we've already described that.
Now, in this caudate nucleus, you've got GABAergic neurons,
and these have an inhibitory hold on the cortex
so that you don't randomly fire the system.
When you lose the GABAergic neurons,
you're going to lose that inhibitory hold,
and so you're going to get random firing of the system,
which is going to result in random purposeless movements,
i.e. chorea.
Again, it's all due to a degeneration
of the GABAergic neurons here in the caudate nucleus.
Now, here's a coronal section from a patient with Huntington's.
Notice that you've lost the caudate nucleus here and here.
Of course, here's the putamen and here's the putamen,
and when you lose the caudate nucleus,
the ventricle opens up because there's more space
because you've lost mass in the brain,
and so you get dilation of the ventricles,
which, again, is called hydrocephalus ex-vacuole.
It is not due to an increase in CSF.
It's due to a loss of brain mass,
and so the key finding, again, in Huntington's disease
is degeneration of the caudate nucleus,
in particular, the GABAergic neurons of the caudate nucleus.
Important to note that this is an autosomal dominant disorder.
It's due to an expanded trinucleotide repeat,
particularly CAG.
You need to know CAG in the Huntington gene.
One very important feature of trinucleotide repeat diseases
is that you can often see anticipation,
which means that you can see the disease occur earlier
in subsequent generations.
So, for example, the grandfather gets it at the age of 60,
but the father gets it at the age of 55,
and so the child anticipates getting the disease earlier,
for example, at the age of 50.
Now, board examiners like you to know
that anticipation is due to further expansion
of the trinucleotide repeat and very high yield.
That expansion occurs during spermatogenesis.
That's particularly high yield.
Of course, patients with Huntington's disease
are gonna have chorea.
Chorea is a rapid involuntary contraction of muscle.
They can also get something called athetosis.
Athetosis is when you get these slow,
involuntary, snake-like movements of the fingers.
Board examiners like you to know about athetosis as well.
This can eventually progress to dementia,
and so you could have dementia
as a component of Huntington's disease.
Eventually, patients also can get depression,
and suicide is a common cause of death.
Moving on to normal pressure hydrocephalus,
this is a possible cause of dementia in adults.
Now, the idea here is that you get increased CSF,
which then dilates the ventricles,
and when you get dilation of the ventricles,
you get stretching of the corona radiata,
which are the nerve fibers that are running
along the edge of the ventricles.
And so when you get stretching of all these nerve fibers,
that's gonna result in a classic triad.
And that triad is urinary incontinence,
gait instability, and dementia.
Now, one of the mnemonics that students like to use
is wet, wacky, and wobbly.
And of course, the wet refers to urinary incontinence,
the wobbly refers to the gait instability,
and the wacky to the dementia.
Now, because this is due to increased CSF,
one of the hallmarks of this disorder is that when you do
a lumbar puncture, the symptoms will improve.
That's particularly high yield.
And taking this one step further,
the treatment then would be to shunt CSF
from the ventricles into the peritoneum,
and that's called a VP shunt.
Now, the last point that I'd like to make
is why is there an increased CSF in these patients?
Well, let's go back and remind ourselves
that the CSF is produced by the choroid plexus
that lines the ventricles,
and that the CSF is drained
by something called arachnoid granulations.
Let's go back.
Here is the pia.
This is the arachnoid.
This is the dura.
There are these arachnoid granulations,
which are outpouchings of the arachnoid
that go through the dura
to access the venous sinuses here.
Now, what happens is the CSF goes up
into the arachnoid granulations
and then gets resorbed into the venous sinuses.
In normal pressure hydrocephalus,
for some unknown reason,
there is decreased absorption of CSF
into the arachnoid granulations.
And so that then results in increased CSF,
which then results in dilation of the ventricles,
which then results in stretching
of the corona radiata, high yield,
stretching of the corona radiata,
which then results in the classic triad
of wet, wacky, and wobbly.
The last disorder that we're going to cover
is spongiform encephalopathy.
This is also a degenerative disease.
However, it's due to accumulation of prion protein.
Now, in order to understand this,
we've got to take a step back
and recall that all of us in our brain
have prion protein,
and it's normally in the alpha helical configuration.
Now, we call that PRPC,
and I've written that here on the board.
Now, if this PRP gets converted to PRPSC,
which basically is in a beta-pleated sheet configuration,
that then results in production of a pathologic protein,
which then causes spongiform encephalopathy.
Now, this pathologic protein
in the beta-pleated conformation creates two problems.
Number one, it will go back to the alpha
and also generate additional beta-pleated conformation,
so it helps to generate more of the pathologic protein.
And number two, when you get this pathologic protein,
it'll accumulate in the neurons.
You can't degrade it.
And when you can't degrade it,
that then is going to result in damage to the neurons,
and the classic damage to the neurons
results in these vaculations in the cytoplasm,
which produce these spongy holes
or these white holes within the brain matter.
And I'll show you a picture of that in a minute.
So this is the basic premise,
and with this in mind,
we can go back and discuss some of the features
of spongiform encephalopathy.
Now, I say here in the text
that a spongiform encephalopathy
is a degenerative disorder
due to accumulation of prion protein.
The pathologic protein,
which again is in a beta-pleated conformation,
that's high yield,
it converts normal protein
into additional pathologic form.
And again, the problem with pathologic form
is that it's not degradable.
Now, because it's not degradable,
it'll damage neurons and glial cells,
and the characteristic hallmark
will be intracellular vacuoles
or spaces within the cells.
Now, here's a picture of spongiform encephalopathy,
and you can see all these white spongy spaces
present within the brain parenchyma.
And again, that's the highlight.
You get spongy degeneration
of the parenchyma of the brain.
The next discussion deals with
how you can actually develop
this beta-pleated conformation,
meaning how is it that you go
from the normal alpha conformation
to the beta-pleated sheet conformation?
And so the answer is
that there are three ways.
The first is sporadic,
where you've got the alpha conformation,
and it just sporadically converts
to the beta form.
Now, this sporadic conversion
is a problem
because that single beta form
will then go back
and convert other alpha proteins
to beta as well.
The betas will pile up,
and then the beta form
will then eventually result
in spongiform encephalopathy.
A second way by which
this transformation can occur
is if you inherit a bad gene.
Now, the idea here
is that you've got
a normal prion gene
that produces a prion protein
in your brain.
If you inherit a bad gene,
that gene can result
in increased conversion
of the alpha form
to the beta-pleated conformation.
Of course,
when you get
the beta-pleated conformation,
that'll then convert
other alphas to beta,
giving you
a spongiform encephalopathy.
And the third way
is transmitted.
Imagine if you get exposed
to the beta-pleated protein,
that beta-pleated protein
can then go into your brain,
convert your alphas into beta,
and then eventually
cause the disease
within the normal brain.
And so that would be transmitted,
and that's why
we classically say
that prion proteins
can also be infectious,
quote-unquote.
The most common form
of spongiform encephalopathy
is CJD.
This is usually sporadic,
which means that it occurs
via sporadic conversion
of the alpha form
to the beta-pleated sheet.
However, it can rarely arise
due to exposure
to prion-infected human tissue.
Now, the classic
historical examples
would be human growth hormone,
which could have been derived
from a patient
who has, for example,
the beta-protein,
and that beta-protein
then gets put
into another patient,
or a corneal transplant,
where the cornea
is given from one patient
who has the beta-protein
to another normal patient.
And this could potentially,
although rarely,
result in CJD.
Now, the hallmark of CJD
is rapid dementia,
very high yield.
The dementia develops
within a very short period
of time, weeks to months,
with the patient
eventually dying,
usually in less than a year.
In addition to the
rapid progressive dementia,
the patients can also
get ataxia
because the cerebellum
can be involved,
and there can also be
startle myoclonus.
Startle myoclonus
is when patients
get involuntary
contractions of muscle
with minimal stimuli,
and so that's called
startle myoclonus.
On EEG,
a hallmark would be
spike wave complexes,
and this is particularly
high yield as well.
And of course,
as I've mentioned,
the dementia is rapidly
progressive,
resulting in death,
usually in less than
one year.
Now, there are a couple
of other spongiform
encephalopathies
to be aware of.
The first is variant CJD.
This is exactly like CJD,
however,
there are two variations.
Number one,
it occurs in younger patients,
and number two,
it's linked to consumption
of meat from cows
that have spongiform
encephalopathy,
mad cow disease.
And so therefore,
these are the two key
features of variant CJD.
And another spongiform
encephalopathy to be aware
of is called
familial fatal insomnia.
This is an inherited form
of prion disease,
which is characterized
by insomnia
and an exaggerated
startle response.
And so these are two
other types of spongiform
encephalopathy
that are important
to be aware of.
And that concludes
our discussion
on degenerative disorders.
Transcription by CastingWords